A Guide to the Papers of James Mercer Garnett 1861-1919
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Mercer Garnett 1861-1919
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
1719
This collection consists of 200 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was purchased from the Peabody Book Shop, 1943 July 9.
Scope and Content Information
The collection contains the papers of Garnett; his son, James Mercer Garnett, Alumni Secretary of the University of Virginia; and his wife, active in the founding of Daughters of the Confederacy.
The papers include Garnett's diary for 1864; a letterbook of armament orders for the Confederacy; sketches of Civil War battles, probably read at Daughters of the Confederacy meetings; sketches of University of Virginia alumni who died in the Civil War; reminiscences of Chancellorsville and Gettysburg by Frederick W. Colston; an issue of the Baltimore Sunday Morning, June 29, 1913, re Gettysburg; and miscellaneous clippings.
There are also Sons of Confederate Veterans correspondence; University of Virginia alumni correspondence; Maryland Alumni Association of the University of Virginia correspondence; and Daughters of the Confederacy correspondence and reports, including a critique, 1905, of a U.S. history textbook unsympathetic to the Southern view of the Civil War and Reconstruction.
An 1893 letter from A.P. Bibb concerning Charlottesville River View Cemetery is written on stationery depicting land for sale by the Locust Grove Investment Company. A law register, 1894-1896, contains a record of cases handled, possibly by Benjamin Kurtz of Baltimore, Md. The 1895 October 28 issue of the Charlottesville Daily Progress contains an article on the burning of the Rotunda.
The collection also contains papers, 1901-1906, prepared for the Woman's Auxiliary, of Memorial Church, Baltimore, by Kate H. Garnett, re: mission work of the Episcopal Church in China, Japan, Liberia, and among North American Indians.
Miscellaneous University of Virginia items include an invitation to finals, 1895; football songs, 1897; final celebration of the Washington and Jefferson literary societies, 1898; closing exercises, 1898; salesman's dummy of "University of Virginia Its history, influence, equipment and characteristics"; summer school brochure, 1909; constitution and by-laws of the Jefferson Literary Society, n.d.; and an address delivered before the Society of Alumni of The University of Virginia, by Muscoe R. H. Garnett, 1850; and a University of Virginia library book of bound pamphlets including Garnett's "Address to the alumni of St. John's College," and extracts from his Civil War diary as published in the Southern Historical Society Papers, XXVII and XXVIII.
Miscellaneous family papers include photographs of James Mercer Garnett, Jr.; Old Blandford Church; and "Aldie," Doylestown, Pa.; proofs of Mercer family genealogy articles; a letter, 1903, from W.R. Mercer, on the family; and an article by Garnett on John Francis Mercer.
Contents List
- Civil War - University of Virginia memorial: MSS biographical sketches of alumni of the University, etc. 1861 (Box-folder 1:1)
- United Daughters of the Confederacy, Baltimore Chapter 1861 Apr 19, typed copy (Box-folder 1:2)
  As Historian...I have been asked to write an account of the tragic events which took place in the city of Baltimore...
- MSS, Armament Orders for the Confederacy 1862-1865 (Box-folder 1:3)
- TMS, The Battle of Sabine Pass, by Mrs. Margaret L. Watson 1863 (Box-folder 1:4)
- MSS, Diary of Capt. James Mercer Garnett (1840-1916) 1864 (Box-folder 1:5)
  [Published in Southern Historical Society Papers. see folder 41]
- MSS, Register of law suits, possibly handled by Benjamin Kurtz of Baltimore, MD 1875-1876 (Box-folder 1:6)
- ALS, 1893 May 18, A.P. Bibb to Prof. [James Mercer] Garnett (1840-1916), 1890-1893 (Box-folder 1:7)
  written on back of a reproduction of 1890 Nov. 29 map of Charlottesville showing holdings of Charlottesville Land Company promoted by A.P. Bibb & Co.
- Correspondence of, or concerning, the United Sons of Confederacy Veterans 1893-1907 (Box-folder 1:8)
- MSS, Papers and membership cards, United Daughters of the Confederacy 1894-1906, printed (Box-folder 1:9)
  including Organization and By-Laws of the Daughters of the Confederacy in Virginia
- Printed invitation, University of Virginia Finals1895 June 9/12 (Box-folder 1:10)
- Printed booklet, Thanksgiving Day Songs dedicated to the University of Virginia Football Team1897 [Nov] (Box-folder 1:11)
- Printed programs, University of Virginia Closing Exercises and Final Celebration of Washington and Jefferson Literary Societies1898 June 12/15 (Box-folder 1:12)
- Sales dummy [front portion of book], Universities and Their Sons: University of Virginia.(Boston, R. Herndon Co., 1900) 1900 (Box-folder 1:13)
- United Daughters of the Confederacy correspondence and papers 1905 (Box-folder 1:14)
  including typescript essays, "Lee and Jackson Contrasted", and "Causes of the Civil War of 1861-1865"
- MSS, Reports to the Women's Auxiliary, [Protestant Episcopal] Memorial Church, Baltimore, by Kate H. Garnett 1901-1906 (Box-folder 1:15)
  re: mission work of the Episcopal Church in China, Japan, Liberia, and among North American Indians
- TMS, The Causes of Secession, by Mrs. Nellie Deans Taylor, United Daughters of the Confederacy 1902 (Box-folder 1:16)
- ALS, W.R. Mercer to James M. Garnett, enclosing postcard views of Doylestown, PA. 1903 Apr 14 (Box-folder 1:17)
  Also included is printed proof of an article, Mercer Family of Virginia and Maryland, by James M. Garnett.
- MSS / printed, The Genesis of Secession, by W. H. Hardy 1903-1904 (Box-folder 1:18)
- Special Supplement to The Baltimore News [1905], printed (Box-folder 1:19)
  featuring the newspaper's new facilities and operations
- Correspondence of, or concerning, the United Sons of Confederate Veterans 1906-1908 (Box-folder 2:20)
- biographies of Mercer Family members 1905, printed proofs (Box-folder 2:21)
- TMS, Charleston Chapter, United Daughters of the Confederacy, criticisms of Egglestons and White's School Histories1905 June 6 (Box-folder 2:22)
- Correspondence of, or concerning, the Maryland Alumni Association of the University of Virginia 1907-1911 (Box-folder 2:23)
  including membership list as of April 1911, and alumni who are not members
- Miscellaneous papers, United Sons of Confederate Veterans [1907-1908] (Box-folder 2:24)
- Correspondence of, or concerning, the General Alumni Association of the University of Virginia 1908 (Box-folder 2:25)
- Accounts and correspondence of, or concerning, the Maryland Alumni Association of the University of Virginia 1908-1917 (Box-folder 2:26)
  including periodic membership lists
- Printed pictorial album, University of Virginia Summer School1909 (Box-folder 2:27)
- Correspondence of, or concerning, the Maryland Alumni Association of the University of Virginia 1910-1911 (Box-folder 2:28)
  including legal and social communications
- Correspondence concerning preparations for annual banquet of the Maryland Alumni Association of the University of Virginia 1911 (Box-folder 2:29)
- Five mounted photographs n.d. (Box-folder 2:30)
  including James Mercer Garnett Jr., Old Blandford Church, and a view of the University of Virginia Lawn and Rotunda
- Printed menu, Annual dinner, Maryland Alumni Association of the University of Virginia 1912 (Box-folder 2:31)
- Bills paid / "acceptances" 1913-1914 (Box-folder 2:32)
  (for annual dinners?)
- Correspondence of, or concerning, the Maryland Alumni Association of the University of Virginia 1917-1918 (Box-folder 2:33)
  including annual dinner
- Scrapbook of newspaper clippings of poems n.d. (Box-folder 2:34)
- Typescript/mimeograph, Reminiscences of Chancellorsville and Gettysburg, by Captain Frederick M. Colston n.d. (Box-folder 2:35)
- Printed advertisement, James McCreery & Co. n.d. (Box-folder 2:36)
- Printed booklet, Constitution and By-Laws of the Jefferson Literary Society[University of Virginia] n.d. (Box-folder 2:37)
- Newsclippings n.d. (Box-folder 3:38)
  re: United Sons of Confederate Veterans
- TMS, John Francis Mercer, Governor of Maryland, 1801-1803, by James Mercer Garnett n.d. (Box-folder 3:39)
- "An Address delivered before the Society of Alumni of the University of Virginia...," by M[uscoe] R[ussell] H[unter] Garnett 1850 June 29 (Box-folder 3:40)
- Address to the Alumni of St. John's College ... on Commencement Day, June 30, 1880, by James M. Garnett. Diary of Captain James M. Garnett... published in Southern Historical Society Papers, vol. xxvii (1899), which is preceded by extracts of the diary published in vol. xxviii (1900) 1880, 1899 (Box-folder 3:41)